-=TLF字幕组=- 荣誉出品
翻译：Jason Lee
翻译：诗琪
翻译：海的风
君临
King's Landing
翻译： lydia萌
校对：Lord Vader
统筹：饭离烨
特效：离太阳只有七步
卡林湾
Moat Cailin
临冬城
WinterFell
绝境长城
The Wall
布拉佛斯
Braavos
弥林
Meereen
根据乔治·R·R·马丁著《冰与火之歌》改编
权力的游戏
第四季   第十集
-=THE LAST FANTASY=-
荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
电视剧编剧
戴维·贝尼奥夫 & D·B·威斯
导演
亚历克斯·格拉维斯
森林之子
You're wearing a black cloak again.
你又披上黑斗篷了
I've been sent to negotiate with you.
我被派來與你方談判
It appears my trusting nature got the better of me.
看來我對你的信任佔了上風
It's happened before.
之前信過你一次
I was hoping your loyalty was real
我曾希望你忠心耿耿
when you pledged yourself to us, Jon Snow.
你曾向我們起誓，瓊恩·雪諾
Truly I was.
我真希望如此
The Halfhand ordered me to join your army
斷掌科林命令我加入你方
and bring back whatever information I could to Castle Black.
把有用的情報帶回黑城堡
He made me kill him so you'd trust me.
他命令我殺了他，換取你們的信任
I was loyal...
我是忠心耿耿的…
to him and to my Night's Watch vows.
忠於他的命令和守夜人誓言
All your vows?
你所有的誓言嗎？
She wasn't enough to turn you, eh?
她不忍心背叛你，對嗎？
Were you enough to turn her?
你忍心背叛她？
She put three arrows in me
我逃跑時
when I escaped.
她射中了我三箭
Did you see her again at Castle Black?
你在黑城堡又見過她嗎？
- Yes. - And?
- 見過
- 然後呢？
She's dead.
她死了
- Your doing? - No.
- 你下的手？
- 不是
We'll drink to her.
我們敬她一杯
Of all the ways I'd kill you,
要你命的方式有千萬種
poison would be the last.
可我不會下毒
- Ygritte. - Ygritte.
- 敬耶哥蕊特
That's not wine.
這不是酒
No, it's a proper northern drink, Jon Snow.
對，這是正統北方飲品，瓊恩·雪諾
You did well. Fought hard.
你幹得不錯，以死相搏
Killed some of our strongest men.
殺了我的幾個大漢
One of our giants went into your tunnel
我方的一個巨人進入了隧道
and never came out again.
就再也沒出來過
Mag the Mighty.
強壯的瑪格
He's dead.
他死了
He killed my friend Grenn.
他殺了我的朋友葛蘭
He was their king.
瑪格是他們的王
The last of a bloodline that stretches back
巨人族的最後血脈，這可以追溯到
before the First Men.
早於先民的年代
Grenn came from a farm.
葛蘭出身農家
- Mag and Grenn. - Grenn and Mag.
- 敬瑪格和葛蘭
- 敬葛蘭和瑪格
Kullback, could I trouble you for something to eat?
庫爾貝克，能給我們弄點兒吃的嗎？
I don't imagine our guest has eaten anything
我猜咱們客人沒吃過東西
for quite some time.
餓很久了
So, you're here to strike a bargain?
那麼，你來是想談和？
Turn your army around and go home.
叫你的軍隊掉頭回家吧
You know I know you're low on arrows,
我知道你們的箭所剩無多
you're low on oil, you're low on men.
火油也沒多少，人手也寥寥無幾
How many are left, 50?
有幾個剩下的，五十個？
I told Tormund and Orell.
我告訴了托蒙德和歐瑞爾
We have more than 1,000 men.
我們有超過一千人
I showed you everything I had.
我讓你見識一下我的儲備
The whole army, 100,000 strong.
全軍十萬之眾
And what did you do?
你們又能做什麼？
You fired on us with everything you had.
你們拼上所有的儲備與我們交戰
It wasn't much. As soon as I saw that,
這些又算什麼？我一望便知
I sent 400 men to climb the Wall,
派了四百人爬長城
an unmanned stretch five miles west of here.
先行部隊向西延伸五里
A lot of them will die climbing,
許多人不慎摔死
but most of them will be over by the end of the day.
但一天下來有更多的人前赴後繼
It's me being honest with you, Jon Snow,
<i>和你開誠佈公的可是我</i>
which is more than you've ever done for me.
<i>你的所作所為和這比起來算什麼？</i>
My people have bled enough.
我的人民付出了足夠的代價
We're not here to conquer.
我們不是來這兒討伐的
We're here to hide behind your Wall.
而是需要越過長城躲避嚴冬
Just like you. We need your tunnel.
正如你們一樣，我們需要隧道
Now we both know that winter is coming.
我們都清楚凜冬將至
And if my people aren't south of the Wall when it comes in earnest,
如果我們子民無法藏身於長城以南
we'll all end up worse than dead.
那麼我們要比凍死還慘
You want to strike a bargain with me?
你要與我談和嗎？
Here's the bargain.
這就是我的條件
You go back, you open the gates to us,
你回去，打開大門
and I swear to you that no one else will die.
我向你保證不會再有人死
Refuse,
如果拒絕
and we'll kill every last man at Castle Black.
我們會把黑城堡殺個片甲不留
Ah!
啊！
Oh, that's why you're here.
你原來就是這個企圖
I reckon you could do it before any of them could stop you.
我猜你可以在他們反應過來得手吧
They'd kill you, of course.
他們當然會宰了你
They'd kill you slow.
讓你慢慢地死
But you knew that when you came in here.
不過你來這裏之前就心知肚明了
Are you capable of that, Jon Snow?
你有這能耐嗎，瓊恩·雪諾？
Killing a man in his own tent when he's just offered you peace?
在我自己的帳篷裏殺了我，而我現在正跟你談和？
Is that what the Night's Watch is?
這就是守夜人的為人嗎？
Is that what you are?
那就是你的為人嗎？
Riders coming!
<i>有騎兵！</i>
- Are you attacking us? - No.
- 你們在向我們進攻嗎？
- 不
It's like you said, we don't have the men.
如你所說，我們沒有人手
Hold! To me! To me!
穩住陣腳！在我周圍！
Stand down!
原地站住！
I said my people have bled enough
我說過我的子民付出了太多代價
and I meant it.
絕無戲言
Round them up.
<i>把他們都綁起來！</i>
Stay with the horses.
<i>和馬匹呆在一起</i>
You're the King-beyond-the-Wall?
你就是塞外之王？
- Do you know who I am? - Never had the pleasure.
- 你認識我？
- 尚未謀面
This is Stannis Baratheon,
此乃史坦尼斯·拜拉席恩
the one true king of the Seven Kingdoms.
七大王國之真命天子
We're not in the Seven Kingdoms and you're not dressed for this weather.
我們可不是七國疆域，你穿的也不是這個季節的行頭
It is customary to kneel when surrendering to a king.
戰敗一方向國王屈膝拜倒乃理所當然之禮儀
We do not kneel.
我們不跪
I'll have thousands of your men in chains by nightfall,
天黑時，你方數千人將被囚禁
have nowhere to put them, have nothing to feed them.
無處收容，無衣無食
I'm not here to slaughter beat dogs.
我們不是來屠殺喪家之犬的
Their fate depends on their king.
他們的命運取決於他們的王
All the same, we do not kneel.
沒什麼區別，我們不跪
Take these men away.
把他們帶走
What's a man of the Night's Watch doing in a wildling camp?
你這個守夜人在蠻族軍隊裏湊什麼熱鬧？
I was sent to discuss terms with the King-beyond-the-Wall.
我被指派來與塞外之王談和
You're speaking to the one true king, boy.
和你說話的才是真正的國王，小子
You will address him as Your Grace.
你要稱呼「陛下」才是
I know he's the king. My father died for him.
我知道他是國王，我父親因他而死
My name is Jon Snow, Your Grace.
我叫瓊恩·雪諾，陛下
I'm Ned Stark's son.
奈德·史塔克之子
Your father was an honorable man.
你父親是個高尚的人
He was, Your Grace.
是的，陛下
What do you think he'd have done with him?
你認為他會如何處置此人？
I was this man's prisoner once.
我曾是他的階下囚
He could have tortured me. He could have killed me.
他本可以折磨我，本可以殺了我
But he spared my life.
<i>但他饒我一命</i>
I think my father would have taken him prisoner,
若父親在世，會把他送進監獄
listened to what he had to say.
聽聽他要說什麼
Very well, then. Take him.
很好，把他帶走
Your Grace.
陛下
If my father had seen the things that I've seen,
<i>如果父親能看到我所看到的</i>
he'd also tell you to burn the dead before nightfall.
他也會讓你在黃昏前燒了屍體
All of them.
全部屍體
I would suggest milk of the poppy
我建議用罌粟汁
to ease his pain, but he is completely insensate.
來幫他止痛，但他毫無知覺
Bloody Martells.
殘忍的馬泰爾家族
The cause appears to be manticore venom.
看樣子是中了獅身蝎尾獸毒
It is. The Death's Head manticore.
是的，死神的頭等獅身蝎尾獸
Yes, I've read a great deal about it.
我讀過有關它的很多資料
It's a horrible poison.
真是種可怕的毒藥
Usually Mantari in origin.
通常起源於曼塔利
Oh! Yes, yes.
哦！是啊
There's nothing to be done.
無藥可救了
Yes, there is.
不，還有救
May I ask what you think you're doing?
你在這兒幹什麼
Saving him.
救他
Your Grace, I wish it were otherwise,
殿下，我也希望不至於此
but Ser Gregor is beyond saving.
但格雷果爵士真的無藥可救
Well, well beyond.
無藥可救
This man is not even a maester,
這人連個學士都不是
let alone Grand Maester.
更別提大學士了
That's for the best.
那樣最好不過
No maester knows how to save him.
學士不會知道怎麼救他
That is exactly the sort of arrogance
殿下，正是如此傲慢自大
that had him expelled from the Citadel, Your Grace.
他才被趕出大學城
His curiosity was deemed dangerous and unnatural.
他好奇於危險和非自然的東西
Rightly so, in my opinion.
我覺得這麼處置他挺恰當
You're dismissed, Grand Maester.
大學士，你可以退下了
But, Your Grace, this is my laboratory.
但是殿下，這可是我實驗室
- Not anymore. - But I--
- 不再是了
<i>- 但是我…</i>
- You can save him? - Difficult to say, Your Grace.
- 你能救活他嗎？
- 陛下，還不好說
But if my past work is any guide...
<i>不過以我過去的經驗來看</i>
...we stand a chance.
還有機會
Do everything you can.
竭盡全力救他
Come to me for anything you need.
有什麼需要儘管告訴我
Thank you, Your Grace.
謝謝殿下
You should know,
<i>但你得知道</i>
the process may change him...
這個過程會改變他…
somewhat.
些許
Will it weaken him?
會把他變弱嗎？
Oh, no.
那不會
Very well, then.
那就好
Not another word.
<i>別再說了</i>
We've been over this. The matter's closed.
我們已經商量完了
I'm opening it again.
我還要繼續商量
You were betrothed to Loras Tyrell.
你跟洛拉斯·提利爾訂婚了
You're still betrothed to Loras Tyrell.
這事板上釘釘
And you will marry Loras Tyrell
你會嫁給他
as soon as Tommen marries Margaery.
很快托曼也會娶瑪格麗
I will not.
我不會嫁
Jaime cannot marry or inherit lands.
詹姆不會娶妻，也不會繼承領土
Tyrion's sentence will be carried out tomorrow.
提利昂的判決明天執行
You have on several occasions made great claims
你已多次為對這個家族的未來…
about your commitment to this family's future.
表達了自己的承諾
Your role in that future
你現在的角色…
is more vital now than it ever was.
比任何時候都至關重要
I don't care.
我不管
I will stay in King's Landing where I belong with my son the king.
我要留在君臨城，在我兒子，國王的身邊
When you were nine years old, I was called to the capital.
你還9歲時，我就被召到王城
I decided to take your brother with me and not you.
我當時決定帶你哥哥隨行，不帶你
You insisted that you would not be left at Casterly Rock
你堅持無論如何
under any circumstances. And if you recall--
不願再留在凱巖城，如果你還記得…
I'm not interested in hearing another one of your smug stories
我沒興趣再聽你那自以為是的故事
about the time you won.
每次你都贏了
This isn't going to be one of those times.
這次你不會再贏
Do you think you'll be the first person
你覺得你是第一個…
dragged into a sept to be married against her will?
被迫結婚的人嗎？
When you marched into the throne room to tell me
當你走進宮殿告訴我…
we'd won the Battle of Blackwater-- do you remember?
我們贏了黑水河之戰，還記得嗎？
I was sitting on the Iron Throne with Tommen.
我當時正跟托曼一同坐在鐵寶座上
I was about to give him essence of nightshade.
準備餵他龍葵
That's how far I was willing to go when I thought
一想起有個邪惡的人要奪走我的兒子
someone awful had come to take my son away.
這麼出格的事我也做得出
Someone awful is coming to take him away.
這個邪惡的人即將來把他奪走
- No. - Joffrey is dead.
- 不
- 喬佛裏已經死了
Myrcella's been sold like livestock.
彌賽菈像個牲畜一樣被賣了
And now you want to ship me off to Highgarden and steal my boy.
現在你要把我送到高庭，偷走我的兒子
My last boy.
我最後一個兒子
Margaery will dig her claws in,
瑪格麗會伸出魔爪…
you will dig your claws in and you'll fight over him
你也會伸出魔爪像野獸一樣與她廝打
like beasts until you rip him apart.
直到你們把他撕成兩半
I will burn our house to the ground before I let that happen.
我把家燒了，也不能讓這種事情發生
And how will you do that?
你要怎麼做？
I'll tell everyone the truth.
我要告訴每個人真相
What truth would that be?
<i>那是個什麼真相？</i>
You don't know, do you?
你還不知道嗎？
You never believed it.
你從來都不信
How is that possible?
那怎麼可能呢，是嗎？
What am I saying? Of course it's possible.
怎麼說呢？那當然是可能的
How can someone so consumed by the idea of his family
你怎麼會如此沉迷於家族觀念
have any conception what his actual family was doing?
連自己家人發生了什麼都不關心？
We were right there in front of you and you didn't see us.
我們就在你眼皮底下，你卻沒發現
One look in the past 20 years,
回首過去20年
one real look at your own children and you would have known.
要是你仔細看看自己的孩子就能發現
Known what?
發現什麼？
Everything they say is true.
他們說的都是真的
- About Jaime and me. - No.
- 有關詹姆和我的事
- 不
- Your legacy is a lie. - No, no, no, no.
- 你的後裔竟個騙局
- 不，不，不是真的
I don't believe you.
我不相信
Yes, you do.
你當然相信
Jaime.
詹姆
You won.
你贏了
One fewer brother. Must be proud of yourself.
又少個弟弟，你很得意啊
There's really nothing you wouldn't do, is there?
你真不擇手段，是嗎？
For my family, no, nothing.
為了我的家族，是的
I would do things for my family you couldn't imagine.
我能做到你無法想像的事
- Tyrion is your family. - He's not.
- 提利昂是你的家人
- 他不是
- You don't get to choose. - I do. So do you.
- 這你無從選擇
- 我能，你也能
You can choose the creature that killed our mother to come into this world--
你都能選擇那個怪物
那怪物殺死了帶他來到人世的母親
Are you really mad enough to blame him for that?
你瘋了嗎，居然為那事責備他？
He didn't decide to kill her. He was an infant.
<i>他沒有決定殺她</i>
<i>他只是個嬰兒</i>
A disease doesn't decide to kill you.
疾病並沒有決定殺人
All the same, you cut it out before it does.
但你還是要消滅它
What do you decide? What do you choose?
你決定了什麼？你選擇了什麼？
The things I did to get back to you,
我回來是為找你
to endure all that, only to find you--
承受一切，我只要找到你
I choose you.
我選擇了你
- Those are words. - Yes.
- 說說而已
- 是的
Like the ones I just said to Father.
就像我對父親說的那些話一樣
I told him.
我告訴了他
Told him what?
告訴他什麼？
I told him about us.
我把我們的事告訴了他
You told him?
你告訴他了？
I told him I won't marry Loras Tyrell.
我告訴他我不會嫁給洛拉斯·提利爾
I told him I'm staying right here with Tommen, with you.
我告訴他，我就要在這跟托曼和你在一起
You think he'll just accept that?
你覺得他能接受嗎？
Go and ask him.
去問問他
What did you say?
你說什麼了？
I don't want to talk about Tywin Lannister.
我不想談泰溫·蘭尼斯特
I don't choose Tywin Lannister.
我沒有選擇他
I don't love Tywin Lannister.
我不愛他
I love my brother.
我愛我的弟弟
I love my lover.
我愛我的情人
People will whisper, they'll make their jokes.
人們會竊竊私語，嘲笑我們
Let them.
讓他們說去吧
They're all so small, I can't even see them.
他們太渺小了，我都不會注意
I only see what matters.
我只注意對我重要的事
Someone will walk in.
有人會進來的
I don't care.
我不管
你面前是「風暴降生」丹妮莉絲
不焚者
彌林的女王
安達爾人，洛伊拿人和先民的女王
大草海的卡麗熙
奴隸解放者和龍之母
謝謝你接見我，陛下
我叫芬尼斯
I can speak the common tongue if you wish.
如果你想的話我可以說通用語
You speak it very well.
你說得非常好
Before you freed me, I belonged to Master Mighdal.
在你解放我前，我屬於米格德爾主人
I was tutor to his children.
我是他孩子們的導師
I taught them languages and history.
<i>我教他們語言和歷史</i>
They know a great deal about your family because of me.
因為我，他們知道了很多關於你的家族
Little Calla is only seven,
<i>小卡拉只有七歲</i>
but she admires you very much.
但是她很崇拜你
I hope I can prove worthy of her admiration.
希望我能證明配得上她的崇拜
What can I do for you?
我能為你做什麼？
When you took the city, the children begged me
你奪下城市的時候，孩子們請求我
not to leave the house.
不要離開房子
But Master Mighdal and I agreed that I must.
但是米格德爾大人和我覺得必須走
So I lost my home.
然後我失去了我的家
Now I live on the streets.
現在我無家可歸
I have outfitted mess halls
我已經供應食物
to feed all former slaves and barracks to shelter them.
給以前的奴隸並建棚屋給他們住
I do not mean to offend, Your Grace.
我無意冒犯，陛下
I went to one of these places.
<i>我去過這些地方中的一個</i>
The young prey on the old.
年輕的掠奪年老的
Take what they want and beat us if we resist.
拿走他們想要的，如果反抗還毆打我們
My Unsullied will make them safe again in short order,
我的無垢者很快就能保證他們的安全
my friend, this I promise you.
我的朋友，我向你保證
Even if they are safe, who would I be there?
即使安全了，在那裏我又是誰
What purpose would I serve?
我存在的意義是什麼
With my master, I was a teacher.
<i>在主人那，我是一個老師</i>
I had the respect and love of his children.
他的孩子們尊重我，愛戴我
What is it that you want from me?
那你想要我做什麼？
Your Grace, I ask you
陛下，我請求你
to let me sell myself back to Master Mighdal.
讓我回到米格德爾大人那裏
You want to return to a man who owned you
你想回到一個擁有你的人旁邊
like a goat or a chair?
像一隻山羊或一把椅子
Please, Your Grace.
請求您，陛下
The young may rejoice in the new world you have built for them,
年輕人會在你為他們建立的新世界裏感到欣喜
but for those of us too old to change,
但是對於我們這些冥頑不靈的人
there is only fear and squalor.
只有恐懼和骯髒
I am not alone.
我不是一個人
There are many outside waiting to beg the same of you.
有很多人在外面有同樣請求…
I did not take this city to preside
我奪取此城，消滅不公正
over the injustice I fought to destroy.
不能讓其繼續當道
I took it to bring people freedom.
我奪取此城是為了給人們帶來自由
But freedom means making your own choices.
但自由意味著做出你們自己的選擇
I will allow you to sign a contract with your former master.
我會同意你和你的前主人簽一個合同
It may not cover a period lasting longer than a year.
它的時效不能超過一年
Thank you, Your Grace.
謝謝，陛下
Thank you.
謝謝
The masters will take advantage of this situation.
奴隸主們會利用這種情況
The men serving them
服侍他們的人
will be slaves in all but name.
行奴隸之實，而無其名
Approach, my friend.
靠近點，我的朋友
我不明白，女王
陛下說你可以靠近點
I have brought you--
<i>我帶來了</i>
He came from the sky.
他從天上飛來
The black one.
<i>黑色的</i>
The winged shadow.
翅膀的陰影
He came from the sky and...
<i>他從天上來然後…</i>
My girl.
<i>我的女兒</i>
My little girl.
我的小女兒
What was her name?
<i>她叫什麼名字？</i>
Zala, Your Grace.
<i>薩拉，陛下</i>
- How old was she? - Three.
- 她多大？
- ３歲
Three.
3歲
沒有龍的消息嗎？
有水手看到他3天前飛過黑崖，女王陛下
之後沒消息了
在地下墓穴等我
They came to us from White Harbor and Barrowton,
<i>他們加入我們，從白港到荒冢屯</i>
from Fairmarket and King's Landing,
從美人市集到君臨
from north and south,
從北方到南方
from east and west.
從東方到西方
They died protecting men, women, and children
他們為保護男人、女人和孩子而死
who will never know their names.
那些永遠不會知道他們名字的人
It is for us to remember them.
<i>我們要記住他們</i>
Our brothers,
<i>我們的兄弟</i>
we shall never see their like again.
<i>我們永遠不會遇到他們那樣的人</i>
And now their watch is ended.
現在他們的守望結束了
Your old blind man patched me up.
你們那個老瞎子幫我包紮
Why?
<i>為什麼</i>
He's sworn to treat all wounded men, friend or foe.
他發誓善待所有的傷者，無論朋友還是敵人
You want me alive so you can torture me?
你們想讓我活著然後來折磨我
No one's gonna torture you.
沒有人會折磨你
So how do we die? Hanging? Beheading?
那我們會怎麼死？絞死？砍頭？
Drop us from the top of the Wall?
<i>從城牆的頂端扔下來?</i>
I don't know what happens to the prisoners.
我不知道會怎麼處理囚犯
Who decides?
誰決定？
I suppose Stannis does.
應該是史坦尼斯
He your king now?
他現在是你的王了
I don't have a king.
我沒有王
You spent too much time with us, Jon Snow.
你和我們呆太久了，瓊恩·雪諾
You can never be a kneeler again.
你不會再下跪了
We're gonna burn the bodies of your dead.
我們要焚燒你們的屍體
Do you want to say any words over them?
有什麼要對他們說嗎？
Words? What kind of words?
說話？說什麼話？
Funeral words. I don't know how the free folk do it.
葬禮的話，我不知道自由民是怎麼做的
Do what?
<i>做什麼？</i>
Say farewell.
告別
The dead can't hear us, boy.
死人聽不到我們，小子
Snow.
雪諾
Did you love her?
你愛過她嗎？
She loved you.
她愛著你
She told you?
她告訴你了？
No.
<i>沒有</i>
All she ever talked about was killing you.
她不停說要殺了你
That's how I know.
<i>這就是我怎麼知道的</i>
She belongs in the North.
她屬於北方
The real North.
<i>真正的北方</i>
You understand me?
明白我的意思嗎？
We can stop. We can rest.
停下來，休息
We'll rest with the three-eyed raven.
沒找到三眼烏鴉不休息
We're not going to make it.
我們到不了了
We're already here.
我們已經到了
Jojen.
<i>玖健</i>
Look, Jojen. Look.
看，玖健，看
Jojen! Come on!
玖健，快點
Help them! Now!
幫他們，快點
Hold on to me!
<i>抓著我</i>
Hang on!
堅持住
- Hodor. - Help them!
- 阿多
- 幫他們
Hodor.
阿多
Hodor!
Hodor.
阿多
Hodor!
Bran!
<i>布蘭</i>
Save yourself, now!
救你自己，快點
Come with me, Brandon Stark.
<i>跟我來，布蘭登·史塔克</i>
He is lost.
他沒救了
Come with me or die with him.
跟我來或者和他一起死
Go with them.
跟他們走
They cannot follow us.
<i>他們進不來</i>
The power that moves them is powerless here.
控制它們的力量在這裏會失效
Who are you?
你是誰？
The First Men called us the children,
先民叫我們森林之子
but we were born long before them.
但是我們出生比他們久遠
Come, he waits for you.
來，他在等你
You're the three-eyed raven?
你就是三眼烏鴉
I've been many things.
我的形態很多
Now I am what you see.
現在是你看到的樣子
My brother, he led us to you and now he--
我的弟弟，他帶我們來找你而現在他
He knew what would happen.
他知道會發生什麼
From the moment he left,
從他出發的那一刻
he knew and he went anyway.
他知道，但還是來了
How do you know?
你怎麼知道？
I've been watching you.
我一直在看著你們
All of you.
每個人
All of your lives.
每個人的生活
With 1,000 eyes and one.
用我一千零一隻眼
Now you've come to me at last,
<i>現在你最終到了我這</i>
Brandon Stark.
布蘭登·史塔克
Though the hour is late.
儘管遲了點
I didn't want anyone to die for me.
我不想任何人為我而死
He died so you could find what you have lost.
他死了你才能找到你丟失的東西
You're going to help me walk again?
你想幫我再次走路？
You will never walk again.
<i>你不會再走路了</i>
But you will fly.
但是你會飛翔
Podrick.
波德瑞克
Where are the horses?
馬在哪裏？
I hobbled them last night.
我昨晚把馬綁上了
What sort of hobble?
怎麼綁的？
A figure eight like you taught me.
八字結，按你教我那樣
If you did it like I taught you,
如果你按我教你那樣綁的
then the horses would be here.
那馬應該還在這
Thieves, maybe?
也許有小偷？
It's at least 30 miles to the Eyrie from here.
鷹巢城離這至少30里地
You're carrying the saddlebags.
行李你背
People coming.
有人來了
You can shit later. There's people coming.
你等會再拉，有人來了
Morning.
早上好
I like your sword.
劍不錯
Are we getting close to the Bloody Gate?
<i>這離血門還遠嗎？</i>
About 10 more miles.
再走大約10里
Did you hear that, Podrick?
聽到了沒有，波德瑞克？
Only 10 more miles to the Bloody Gate.
再走10里就到血門了
Are you a knight?
你是騎士嗎？
No.
不是
But you know how to use that sword?
但你會使劍？
I do.
會
Does it have a name?
劍叫什麼？
Oathkeeper.
守誓劍
Mine's Needle.
我的劍叫縫衣針
Good name.
名字不錯
Who taught you how to fight?
誰教你戰鬥的？
My father.
我父親
Mine never wanted to.
我父親從不想讓我學
Said fighting was for boys.
他說戰鬥是男孩子的事
Mine said the same.
我父親也這麼說
But I kept fighting the boys anyway.
但我還是繼續跟男孩戰鬥
Kept losing.
<i>總是輸</i>
Finally my father said, "If you're going to do it,
最後，我父親說：「要戰鬥的話」
you might as well do it right."
「還是像樣學學吧」
Seven blessings.
七神保佑
I'm Brienne of Tarth. This is Podrick Payne.
我是塔斯的布蕾妮，他是波德瑞克·派恩
You want something?
你想幹什麼？
That's Sandor Clegane. The Hound.
他是桑鐸·克裏岡，「獵狗」
You're Arya Stark.
你是艾莉亞·史塔克
I asked if you wanted something.
我問你想幹什麼？
I swore to your mother I would bring you home to her.
我向你母親發誓，會帶你回家見她
My mother's dead.
我母親死了
I know.
<i>我知道</i>
I wish I could have been there to protect her.
我只恨沒能在她身邊保護她
You're not a northerner.
你不是北境人
No, but I swore a sacred vow to protect her.
不是，但我立下了神聖誓言要保護她
Why didn't you?
那你怎麼不保護她？
She commanded me to bring Jaime Lannister back to King's Landing.
她命令我帶詹姆·蘭尼斯特回君臨城
You're paid by the Lannisters.
你收了蘭尼斯特的錢
You're here for the bounty on me.
<i>你是來殺我領賞金的</i>
I'm not paid by the Lannisters.
我沒收蘭尼斯特的錢
No?
沒有？
Fancy sword you've got there.
劍不錯啊
Where'd you get it?
哪來的？
I've been looking at Lannister gold all my life.
蘭尼斯特的金子我看了一輩子
Go on, Brienne of fucking Tarth.
說吧，什麼狗屁塔斯的布蕾妮
Tell me that's not Lannister gold.
說這不是蘭尼斯特的金子
Jaime Lannister gave me this sword.
這劍是詹姆·蘭尼斯特送我的
The Bloody Gate is 10 miles.
血門還有10里
I swore to your mother by the old gods--
我向你母親發誓，以舊神…
I don't care what you swore.
我不管你發了什麼誓
- Arya! - You heard the girl.
- 艾莉亞！
<i>- 你聽見了</i>
- She's not coming with you. - She is.
- 她不會跟你走的
- 她會的
You're not a good listener.
你沒聽清楚吧
That Valyrian steel?
瓦雷利亞鋼？
I always wanted some Valyrian steel.
我一直想弄點瓦雷利亞鋼
Come with me, Arya. I'll take you to safety.
跟我走，艾莉亞，我會帶你到安全的地方
Safety? Where the fuck's that?
安全的地方？那他媽是哪？
Her aunt in the Eyrie is dead. Her mother's dead.
她在鷹巢城的姨媽死了，她母親死了
Her father's dead. Her brother's dead.
她父親死了，她哥哥死了
Winterfell is a pile of rubble.
臨冬城成了亂石堆了
There is no safety, you dumb bitch.
沒有安全的地方，你個傻婊子
You don't know that by now,
你還不明白嗎？
you're the wrong one to watch over her.
她不應該由你來照顧
And that's what you're doing?
那應該由你來？
Watching over her?
照顧她？
Aye, that's what I'm doing.
是，現在我在照顧她
I have no wish to kill you, Ser.
我不想殺你，爵士
I'm not a knight.
我不是騎士
Arya!
艾莉亞！
- Where is she? - She was just here.
- 她去哪了？
<i>- 剛才就在這</i>
Why weren't you watching her?
你為什麼不看著她？
I was watching you. I thought you might need some help.
我在看著你，我以為你會需要支援
Which way, Pod? Which way did she go?
哪邊，波德？她往哪邊走了？
I think that way.
可能是那邊
Arya!
<i>艾莉亞！</i>
You still here?
你還在這？
Big bitch saved you.
大個婊子救了你
I don't need saving.
我不用人救
No, not you. You're a real killer.
你確實不用，你是真正的殺手
With your water dancing
會跳水之舞
and your Needle.
還有縫衣針
You gonna die?
你會死嗎？
Unless there's a maester hiding behind that rock,
除非石頭後面藏著個學士
aye,
是的
I'm done.
我完了
I'd skin you alive for wine.
現在要是能有酒，讓我活剝了你都行
Fuck water.
去他媽的水
Killed by a woman.
居然被女人殺了
I bet you like that.
你肯定喜歡
Go on,
去吧
go after her.
跟她走吧
She'll help you.
<i>她會幫你</i>
Going it alone,
獨自在外
you won't last a day out there.
<i>你一天都活不了</i>
I'll last longer than you.
我會活得比你久的
You remember where the heart is?
還記得心臟在哪嗎？
Fuck it.
去他的
I'm ready.
我準備好了
Go on, girl.
來吧，小妞
Another name off your list.
名單上再劃掉一個名字吧
You kept promising me.
你總說會殺我
I cut down your butcher's boy.
我砍死了屠夫的兒子
The ginger.
紅頭髮那個
He was begging for mercy.
他求我饒命
"Please, Ser. Please don't kill me.
「求您了，爵士，求您別殺我」
Please, please."
「求求您了」
Bled all over my horse.
<i>血濺了我的馬一身</i>
Saddle stunk of butcher's boy for weeks.
<i>好幾個星期馬鞍都是他的臭味</i>
And your sister.
還有你姐姐
Your pretty sister.
你漂亮的姐姐
I should have taken her.
<i>我應該幹了她</i>
That night the Blackwater burned.
黑水河燃燒那夜
I should have fucked her bloody.
我應該狠狠地操她
At least I'd have one happy memory.
<i>至少也能有一段快樂的回憶</i>
Do I have to beg you?
要我求你嗎？
Do it.
動手吧
動手啊
Kill me.
殺了我
Kill me!
殺了我！
殺了我吧！
Kill me!
殺了我啊！
Oh, get on with it, you son of a whore.
噢，要殺就殺吧，狗娘養的
Is that any way to speak about our mother?
你都管我們母親叫狗娘？
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛？
What do you think I'm doing?
你覺得我在幹嘛？
A galley's waiting in the bay bound for the Free Cities.
港口裏有帆船接應，去自由貿易城邦
- Who's helping you? - Varys.
- 誰幫你找的？
- 瓦裏斯
- Varys? - You have more friends than you thought.
- 瓦裏斯？
- 你的朋友比你想的多
There's a locked door at the top of the stairs.
台階頂上有一扇鎖著的門
Knock on it twice, then twice again.
敲兩下，然後再敲兩下
Varys will open.
瓦裏斯會開門
I suppose this is good-bye, then.
那這就是告別了
Farewell, little brother.
永別了，弟弟
Jaime.
詹姆
Thank you for my life.
你的恩情，今生感激不盡
Quickly now.
快走吧
Tywin?
泰溫？
My lion.
我的獅子
I'm sorry.
抱歉
Tyrion.
提里昂
Put down the crossbow.
放下十字弓
Who released you?
誰把你放了？
Your brother, I expect.
我猜是你哥哥
He always had a soft spot for you.
他總是對你心軟
Come, we'll go and talk in my chambers.
走，去我屋裏談
This is how you want to speak to me, hmm?
你就想這樣跟我談？
Shaming your father has always given you pleasure.
<i>虧你父親還一直哄你開心</i>
All my life
我這一生
you've wanted me dead.
你一直想讓我死
Yes.
沒錯
But you refused to die.
<i>但你不想死</i>
I respect that.
我尊敬你
Even admire it.
甚至敬佩你
You fight for what's yours.
<i>你全力為自己爭取</i>
I'd never let them execute you.
我不會讓他們處決你的
Is that what you fear?
你是在怕這個嗎？
I'll never let Ilyn Payne take your head.
<i>我不會讓伊林·派恩砍你的頭的</i>
You're a Lannister.
你是蘭尼斯特
You're my son.
你是我兒子
I loved her.
我愛過她
Who?
誰？
Shae.
雪伊
Oh, Tyrion.
得了，提里昂
- Put down that crossbow. - I murdered her.
- 放下十字弓
- 我殺了她
With my own hands.
親手殺的
- It doesn't matter. - Doesn't matter?
- 那不重要
- 不重要？
She was a whore.
她是個妓女
- Say that word again... - And what?
- 再說這話我就…
- <i>就怎樣？</i>
You'll kill your own father in the privy?
在廁所裏殺了你父親？
No.
你不會
You're my son.
你是我兒子
Now, enough of this nonsense.
好了，鬧夠了
I am your son and you sentenced me to die.
我是你兒子，而你判我死刑
You knew I didn't poison Joffrey,
你明知我沒給喬佛裏下毒
but you sentenced me all the same.
但你還是判我死刑
- Why? - Enough.
- 為什麼？
- 夠了
We'll go back to my chambers
<i>回我房間</i>
and speak with some dignity.
有點尊嚴再談
I can't go back there. She's in there.
我不能回去，她在那
You're afraid of a dead whore?
你怕死妓女？
You shot me.
你居然朝我射箭
You're no son of mine.
你不是我兒子
I am your son.
我是你兒子
I have always been your son.
我永遠都是你兒子
What have you done?
你幹什麼去了？
Quickly.
快走
Trust me, my friend. I brought you this far.
相信我，朋友，事已至此了
I want to see the captain.
我要見船長
You're seeing him.
我就是
I want to go north to the Wall.
我想向北，去長城
No, you don't.
你不能去
I can pay.
我可以付錢
There is nothing in the North but ice and war and pirates.
北境只有冰、戰爭和海盜
I wouldn't need a cabin. Please.
我不佔船艙，求您了
I could work scrubbing the floors.
我可以幹活，擦甲板
I'm not going north, child. I'm going home.
我不去北境，孩子，我要回家
- Where's home? - The Free City of Braavos.
- 你家在哪？
- 布拉佛斯的自由城邦
Wait. I have something else.
等等，我還有別的
More silver won't make a difference.
再多銀子也沒用
It's not silver. It's iron.
不是銀子，是鐵
This...
這…
How did you--
你怎麼會…
Valar morghulis.
<i>Valar morghulis（凡人皆有一死）</i>
Valar dohaeris.
<i>Valar dohaeris（凡人皆需侍奉）</i>
Of course, you shall have a cabin.
沒問題，你可以住一間船艙
-=TLF字幕组=-
谢谢观赏
TLF中文字幕站 http://sub.eastgame.org/
微博地址：http://weibo.com/tlfsubs
豆瓣小站：http://site.douban.com/127446/